Okay, you guys ready to go you guys all pumped up after the key notes this
morning some pretty awesome stuff.
First of all I wanted to thank you guys for coming to build conference today and also thank you for
coming to this session I will to a little bit of slide's
up-front but for the most part I have I think let's see nine demos that
...a each have five or six part so this will be an extremely
demo filled session...some of my demos were failing this morning and we got a
backup machine so I'm on the edge of my see to see if
this'll actually all work we do have some
...so I don't I don't think you should be worried we will be able to see everything I just might need
...between machines a little bit so first of all let me introduce
myself my name is amanda silver I'm the director of program management for the team that
works on client applications within visual studio so,
that actually covers all applet any tool for building
app for windows applications across all of the different windows
devices the native, nativesample experience things like that ieee.
So, the...twelve tools that you guys might have used in internet
explore now edge that is also on my team as well as the type script
programming language and the tools for patchy cordova I also work very closely with this
...and team so I will be demo ing some of that stuff for you today so,
that kind of covers who I am...we will
...jump right in the please do submit...evaluation
this actually does help me going forward of for a future talk...I, you know,
can improve each time?
But, let's kind of jump right in so the first question is why
build apps how many of you guys have built a mobile app so far.
Okay, not everybody in the audience and in fact I have had
the opportunity to talk to sixty-seven...companies
in the last three six months having conversations like this about
different strategies for building mobile applications and one of the things that I'm finding
across all of the companies that I talked to is that a majority of them are at the
needy of the curve in terms of embracing mobile technology and building mobile
solutions and what I mean by that is that they have built one or two
or maybe three mobile apps thus far and they might have done it by hiring
a mobile specialist firms so they actually outsource the project to another
a external company to build this mobile app and
they're now in the process where they realize that hey, you know, I
actually think we have ten fifteen in some cases hundreds of mobile apps that we have to
build now and we actually need to bring this in-house and make it more
a central part of...of our practice
does that kind of reflect where you guys are any of you yes no
...yes okay I see a couple hands in the back of the room the other
thing that I'm finding as I talked to in particular small isv
to think about it as startups who are building applications because
they want to have a mobile app based business and for them they really
want to get a mobile app out to market as quickly as they possibly can so
they can basically build a min viable product and test the business model and see if it's
actually working with customers get that out there and then actually refine so on so
forth so I think we're finding that there are a lot of companies that are now in this
me of the curve where they are, you know,
they might have dabbled mobile development to start or they've even assigned a swat team within
the organization to go build some mobile apps but they're now starting to make that
a much larger part of their regular it practice and development practice?
So, one of the things that I've also seen and I think gartner and forrester and a bunch of the
analysts also reflect this is that the
technology is moving much closer to the customer so in terms of, you know,
what your job is as a developer it might used
to be that a lot of developers had to just...internally facing employee facing
applications and they didn't actually really interact with the customer very much I would say that
...more and more often I'm seeing that actually the internal it departments actually
have to build mobile applications that are customer-facing and they're much more engaged in
that in that process now many of you guys have probably
been in development for many years tens of years...possibly decades and,
I think that, you know, a lot of us when we started in the industry
we're very used to the client-server kind of technology and this notion that we had
a user interface and we had some kind of back-end system that we were pumping all of that data
...and in fact if I think about governmental agencies,
for example, a lot of them are still doing that process with
the paper process you fill out a form and there's somebody who's in the back-office
is actually uploading that to a server and that goes into a database that we
would call a system of record so it basically catalogues kind
of what has happened with that particular employee or customer but,
there's very little authentic
...interaction between the developer and what they've built and the customer or
the person who is interacting with that workflow process?
What we're certainly seeing is that there's an increasing number of people who have to build these
systems of engagement and I think about this in with...good
the app examples one my favorite one is the
crispy cream hot like app...you guys are familiar with that
app came out a couple years ago I love this app not because I'm a big
...reader although I do like my...
and but because the idea behind this app is that
if you're trucker driving down the road and you want to get hot
...this'll actually send the push notification to your
up to your device to tell you there's a hot
...nearby come to crispy cream and they didn't initially as a marketing
exercise to see if they could actually have more interaction engagement with their
customers
and but over time they found that this was actually very strategic application for them and that
it actually was something that they needed to kind of incorporate and improve and they wanted to get
a lot of that data and how many of you guys are staying in hotels right now those of you who
are not local so hotels on my way down the web displaying virgin
america and they have those nice little tv screens and lot-of commercials that come up but, you know,
in front of you probably three or four of the commercials I was watching
were commercials for the hotels?
Now why would the hotel want you to download
...app the way that they marketed in the, you know,
commercial was it delivers a much better consumer experience in it does you
can interact with the concierge you can reserved room service or other things like
that but the hotel also gets a lot of insight into what you do
as a customer so increasingly we're seeing that people need to build these systems of engagement so
that's really what how I think about mobile applications so the first question
is when you start building a mobile application where you start.
Now one of the things that I think we've observed is that.
Basically there are a lot of mobile applications that you're going to end up building if I build something like that hotel
concierge app there might be a reservation system a room service system, you know,
all different kinds of workflows and processes
that I would want to interact with as a customer and each one of those could be an independent app they
could be consolidated into a single app but the idea is that if you build those
services and workflows and processes and you basically make that, you know,
really solid and you get the deb apps practices running very
well against that then you can actually let a thousand flowers bloom you can actually let a
lot of websites or mobile apps get built against
those back-end services so I think a lot of people in the industry are kind
of recognizing that really starts with the back-end and that's kind
of where I'm going to start so in terms of building these back-end services we
call the micros services and in asher as of about you know,
three or four weeks ago this was basically what we had to offer websites you
could build mobile services you could build a you could manager api
...api management services or you could use this talk services and about
...march twenty third of we basically consolidated all
of those things into the asher app service so now there's
one service that will allow you to build a web application mobile application
and api app...logic app logic...would be for a workflow process
hidden so now let's get into the front-end they're basically two different strategies that
we see people taking when it comes to building mobile applications
number-one they start with building native platform native platform technologies
native apps using the native tools for each of the devices that
they target so they get full access advice capabilities they get fantastic
performance
...for those apps if they continue to...and it's very
customized per device on the other end of the spectrum we see people.
Building from web technology so they start with a website
maybe and they might optimized that website for mobile
experiences but still be contained into the browser now the challenge
with native based solutions is that if I target ios first and
then have to do a complete port and, you know, building using the native tools
eighty android studio the to target android and then for windows I
then have to do it again at the challenge for web technologies is that,
you know, you're especially if you're building for browser container
your very much constrains to watch that what that browser container is capable
of so you can't really access the native device capabilities so from our
perspective we recognize that this is where a lot of people are coming frombut,
we don't think that you have to be a limited by those constraints so
there are a lot of people...starting with reach experiences on windows that starts with dot
net or cplus-plus you can also build a native of windows application using javascript
but for desktop applications you would start with wpf or the universal windows apps?
Windows universal apps
the and we cplus-plus you could build with when thirty-two.
But, if you wanted to take those that dot net expertise
...partnered with a company called...I see many of you guys have them and...
on in the room that's great how many of you guys have heard of them are and before.
Most of...ok so I'll show you guys quick demo but some of you still haven't seen it and
then we've also introduce new tools for visual cplus-plus for
crush platform development and kid...appear we has it has a session that
will go deep on this I will show you a number of demos as well on this.
For the breadth of devices if I start in the web space and it starts with the browser based
applications but what we have been working on over the past year we announced it
and...head last year is the very early alpha of the visual
studio tools for patchy cap cordova I'm very excited to announce that today
we have reached rc for visual studio twenty fifteen so now we have a
go live license you can actually go ahead and build production ready apps
...using the visual studio twenty fifteen rc using the tools for
...cordova and I will go into a bit of what he tools for patchy
...but first I'm going to kind of jump into demo so before I show you guys
...I'm going to show you the measure app service real quick.
Let me see which machine my own.
So, this is the asher app service you could you guys can actually go and hit this now and
try the asher apps service and.
This starts with just you can actually
selecting app service were building mobile apps today so I can go ahead and
create this app now I need to login.
I didn't do this earlier but.
I'm signing in with my
...microsoft account but I can use the other accounts as you could see and then that
actually just creates and...service on the back-end that I could then
connects with a mobile application and if we
go here you can actually see that the app services already up and running
the absolute I'm going to show you today we've already gone through this process.
The cool thing about this is.
I can also the see it and edited
using visual studio online monaco but this is basically the same
technology that the visual studio code that we just announced in the keynote a minute ago
...using the same exact technology to connect to
this back-end service and show us the code here I'm sure...a lot of people hitting
this service right now because we just made the announcement so that might be why it's a little bit slow but,
you can see I can go into the
controllers and I can look at something like that to do item controller and I can just start,
you know, author, you know,
editing this code immediately and start working against the back-end service
so next thing I'm going to do is jump into the apps itself that I'm going
to kinda bring you through...is number four.
You guys see before you multiple.
Mobile devices yes everybody can see okay, so, the basic scenario going to show you is
...huber type scenario the idea is that we have a shuttle application that
is corporate shuttle service and we have two different apps we have
an app for the consumer and then we have an app for the...now let's just bring up the
my shuttle dot biz for each one of the apps for each one of the devices.
And, as you can see
the layout for each one of these apps is actually distinct per device.
Now this is a consumer app so I want to make sure that my
consumers that interact with this app in the app store
get what feels like a very native experience for their app as you can see for the
windows device this is windows eight-point one so.
I will show you guys...windows ten...application in just a second but this one was
authored using eight-point one...you can see that we have the pivot control if we look
at the navigations you can see that the navigation looks verywindows
like if we go to the ip iphone application you can see that the navigation
is along the bottom which is a very iphone kind of way to do it and,
for the android application you can see the navigation is
along the top each of these looks and feels very native for the device if we look at
the transitions for the ios device and the transitions for the android
device that comes in from this side for the ios device and it comes in from the bottom for
the android device so it is a very native look and feel and this is built using
...this particular application
next what I'm going to do is go ahead and show you guys the driver version of the application.
So, let's just bring up the driver version.
So, this is basically the caddy who's driving a car
what does he do when he wants the user
...you know, we started ride so we could go ahead and start a service
...start arrived and we can finish that and you can see that I get the
...information I can go to the signature I can go ahead and
sign this my...my nail was getting the way there but,
that actually takes that invoice posts it to the office
three-six five api which there a lot of sessions on a throughout build
...to sharepoint server in the back back-end now.
So, what you'll see here is that the app looks and feels exactly the
same across the different devices now for this app because it's for the
employees my employees of the my shuttle service I want that
app to have the same look and feel across the different devices because?
Of training purposes because of support purposes I actually want to keep
the costs down for this particular device pick particular app
so for this one we're using tools for patchy cordova now if I go into the...
biz the app again and I go ahead and request.
...you can see that sends a push notification using v adder
app service the mobile services to my android device if I go ahead
and accept it you can see that this will actually send another push notification to
my windows device I could even go ahead and update the
location so you see the pin on the android device there I can update my location
you see
...updates right there is a very kind of live experience.
That's off-screen but.
As you can see in just a second it
should show us the pin being updated so this is using signal
...which is a part of esp dot net for real-time communications so,
now let's jump into how this application is being built by notify the client that I'm
We can see that the vehicle has arrived and then I can go out and get the vehicle
driver allows me to accepted and then we can go ahead and
take the ride send the signature except...get sent to the back-end
within invoice so now I'm going to take this android device
and I'm going to attach it to this pc that I have here.
I'm going to show you the applications that we built.
So, let me close this.
And, let's jump to seven.
Ok.
So, first thing visual...this...little bit dangerous to do in
a demo but I actually have...running here and the reason I have...
running is for those of you who have built mobile applications you guys know
that it's very challenging together get your dev box set up with all of the dependencies that you
have that you need to build mobile applications, you know, for an android application
I could end up having twenty-something dependencies that I have to install uniquely what
we've done is we've actually simplified the acquisition experience and the deb
setup experience...box...experience into visual studio
with consolidated it so what you can see here.
Is that under the cross platform mobile device...mobile development node we have
...if I want to build...using csharp and salmon we have html javascript if I want to build
using apache cordova we have the cross platform cplus-plus components and then we
have common components that are used across all of these the
different solutions including the visual studio emulator for android which I'll show you guys a
little bit later but this is just to show you guys that it makes it really easy to get your
...set-up and to keep that dev box running
and in good condition so I'm going to?
Go back and I'm going to.
Just cancel
set up so that I don't work my machine further.
And, now I'm going to jump into the solution so.
Witness...and...will start with the native applications so the windows
the android and ios applications that I built using salmon with these
amin extension for visual studio which is now included as part of the visual studio
set up so you don't need to go to some other url to go find if you just install
visual studio as part of setup you'll be able to check examine I now have
templates for android applications I also have templates for ios applications
as well so I can target iphone so I've already done that my solution
now what we start with is at a common core
of logic for the application that is built-in dot net that works
across all three of the different mobile operating systems and that is done using portable
class libraries what you can see here is that things like this service agents can you guys
will see that...the service agents are defined in a common way so if I think
about something like a issuing a ride I want to initiate
a new ride that doesn't need to be different across the different devices that could actually be the
same exact code running on each of the client's but, it's authored using dot net?
The other thing that you can see here is that.
The view models even the view models so if I think about something like the vehicle detail
...model this is basically defining a common view
model that is common across all three of the different operating systems and
then we really have only the finessed presentation
...that chooses how it should be rendered for each one of the devices and in fact,
you know, true story.
As...three days ago we didn't have a version of this
app for windows ten we built
it three days ago and the way that we could do that and I'll show you guys this
and just a second the way we could do that is because most of the logic was defined in these portable
class libraries.
So, next thing I'm going to do is just show you guys how you can actually do
this with the portable class libraries if we go to the properties even see that witness...
extension I can create a portable class library that can go across all the different windows
devices as well as a android and ios what's missing there
is windows ten that does not mean that your portable class library will not work on windows
...it actually works used to have to check a box to
get to work we will add the check box just in case, you know,
between now and when we are tm the product so this is outstanding work for us
in visual studio but that's basically how I can define a portable
class library across all of these different solutions so now what I can do is go
ahead and view that code map for this assembly so this is
the new tool in visual studio twenty fifteen that allows me to quickly visualize
what's going on in my application and I can look at the
assemblies referencing this is actually going to build this up dynamically?
you will see very quickly that each of the projects that are in the solution
are referencing this core dl.
And, it will show it to us in just a second.
Command.
Indexing this does take a little bit to compute but once you do it's pretty amazing
...you can see here.
Command.
...faster earlier.
There is a sub-set but it is pretty broad
...it's actually.
Sorry...question was.
The question was and, we now see it coming up the question was because it's a portable
classed library do you have to limit the
api that the portable classed library can access to make it a portable
class library the answer is yes but it is a very broad subset and
we're working with the examine community and the opensource dot net community to make sure that
...as broad as it can be we think it's pretty good but,
we're always looking for those last few
...that are kind of important so you have feedback on that feel free to get
it to me as you can see here I have for the native applications I
...referencing the my shuttle dot client dot core
...in the universal app for windows eight and eight-point one I
mean windows eight-point one phone and windows eight-point...
forms application the ios and windows ten universal application
that I also have a wpf client that I've also built against
this same portable class library I'm not going to talk about the...client today but, that will be
in the solution that we make a publicly available now if we go
into the native app mobile applications you can see that for the windows
...one applications what we've done is we have different projects but we have
shared projects a shared code across these different projects so
if I go in here you can actually see that if we look at the about dot example file.
This will just take one second to load but you can see that I can actually use
the same exact example file across the windows and
windows phone device...make this come down so I can actually
go ahead and change that to be a windows phone
...rendering and you will see in just a second that will we
render for the windows phone and you will see that it's basically the same exact
screen and same exact sample being shown across to the windows phone now let's talk about the
windows ten application so in the windows ten application we can do
basically the same mechanism if we go into the views.
We can look at the vehicle detail page.
As I'm doing that so as you can see here we are currently rendering this
for the five-inch phone this is all-new functionality in visual studio
twenty fifteen and I can then go ahead and change that same
view to look at the tablet and now this is only at
thirty three percent so if we increase that a little bit you guys should be
able to see what it looks like in the tablet view?
...you can see here what you should be able to see here is that we actually can use
Various view state triggers to basically initiate this what I'm going to do is just show you
guys it running in thephone emulator and the windows simulator
side-by-side so this is that app running side-by-side as you guys have seen
previously in windows ten all applications including modern applications
are windowed so this will start initial initially in a windowed mode but I can make
a go full-screen and as you can see here one of the benefits of developing on a
...device is I can actually use my
finger here to the scroll to the bottom of the available cars and I can
see the my rides tab that is the tablet view it's actually on
the right-hand side and then you can see if I select this you can see what the vehicle detail
view looks like and you can see what it looks like in the phone so we built
this three days ago yes there's we can make the right a little bit better but,
you know, you can see that were actually using the same kind of technology the for
the windows devices ok so that's the windows applications
and they're going to be a lot of sessions and in fact just segment is here and I think
he will to be talking about this little bit later on how you can actually customize
your example across the different, different devices.
So, I'm just going to shut this down.
Okay,
now let's jump into these ample port the ...and portions for the android application
...the ios application so first I'm going to kind of look at the android
application and if I go into the views.
Main view and I just start typing.
You can actually see that I have intel's sense here based on this
...extension that gets me the latest android capabilities
so I get all of the same visual studio productive development experiencebut,
for android and ios applications so that's
pretty great and next thing I'm going to do is show you the vehicle
...that same screen that we just looked at in the.
Windows application and I'm going to bring up...designer.
Now after this renders in just a second.
Let's see let's closer than reopen it.
You can see that this is kind of what the screen looks like for in this case the galaxy
nexis
if I went ahead and change this to the let's see...five.
You will see in just a second that...re render for the...five so I get a
...wig kind of experience for building these screens
...android applications.
I can change the layout,
for example, change it back you can see that happens same goes for
the ios applications if I go into the ios application.
You can see that this is using the.
My shuttle using
serious that mgm cross so that's a common the.
Common.
You know,...library this
is using the my shuttle dot client dot core as we talked about earlier.
And, then if I go into the views.
Sorry the storyboards view you can actually see that I get the same kind of
...wig experience we have a full toolbox that I can do, you know,
drag-and-drop all kinds of controls on to this design experience and in fact
for ios it's not just a per screen designer this is actually a full
storyboards designer like what you see...x code so if I
zoom out you can actually see that I have the full story board of
for the application defined in this in this in visual
studio for my ios application so that's pretty cool
...what you guys were kinda interested in cn ok so the next thing I'm going to show
you guys is we're going to do a deep dive into the cplus-plus
stuff before let's see how we do...the.
How do you guys feel about skip in some slides and just keep demo
in good with that okay if we have slide's time at the end I'll go back to
the end ok...next...I'm going to do is just shut down this project?
And, reopen another one I
can't have all these things running at the same time unfortunately just gets too.
Clogged up a little bit if I had a full beefy desktop machine it would be no problem
that this is a lightweight aces tablet.
So, next I'm going to open the cplus-plus version of these
amin project and I'm going to deploy that same applications so I
talked about earlier how we've also introduced support for
the across platforms cplus-plus now how many of you...kobe cplus-plus
...you guys okay and one of the reasons why we did this isn't talking to our
office team as they were taking their code base twenty fifteen-year code
...to mobile devices across ios
and android they basically needed to take that code base mobile so,
we started building this for the officeteam what you can see here
if we go we look at this application this is all cplus-plus?
If we go into the project properties you can see that visual studio supports
...and it supports gcc this is a new world so,
this is kind of a big deal for those of you who have
a coded in cplus-plus before and.
So, I'm just going to keep that there
and I'm going to deploy this to the samsung device that is attached here.
Now what this is doing is it has a common cplus-plus component...
this case it's an open gl component that I'll show you guys in a second that is being used in this
application and then it has a front-end that's defined using the cameron so,
this should be deployed to this device in just a.
And, it's capping the application to the device I will jump to the...vision.
As it does the installation
...it should get loaded in just a second.
So, we're going to show you guys and just a second is an open gl the.
Experience.
It as I request this car you can see that this is actually
open gl defined in visual studio running on the android device with
...in front-end so once that vehicles requested we're
...to go ok so now I can jump back to.
The demo...to show you another application real quick.
Let's step debugging.
And, I'm going to show you the bing maps control so.
Let me go into here.
Will debug...maps?
So, this is the real-life bing maps control that the developers
...microsoft the have built and,
I will show you that running on the device in just a second so what we've done here
is we've taken that application we have not modify it so we really just taken
...application but we have done is we've created a small
wrapper which is a visual studio project that is wrapped around that cplus-plus
project selection launch it and deploy it on to the device and actually attach the debugged.
So, if I go ahead and just press...we can go ahead and deploy...to the device.
And, what this is going to do is it's just a tester for the map control
itself?
So, if we jump to the will for vision let's see.
You guys see that on the android...loading now.
It's in the process of loading.
And, the its loading symbols here so if we come back to.
You guys can see that it is set seven still loading
symbols it's attaching in the debug mode and now we can
go to the android device and you can see that
it's loading it's in the process of loading the map.
If we go to seattle.
This will take just a second you can actually see the seattle
map the getting loaded here I
can pan around you can see I'm going back to seattle so,
you can actually see that native cplus-plus
...component is running and debugging now
if I'm starting to load the raster is
a shun images for the traffic control and,
if we go back to seven you can actually see that I have hit a break point here.
Go ahead and hit...ten a couple times.
You can see that the stepping is actually pretty fast so we're using gb on the back-end
...to do this native,
nativestepping as well all right so now I talked about
the android emulator before what I'm going to show you next is again
a cplus-plus component using open gl but in this case.
Let me just
the shut this down stop the debugging I'm going to just kill this.
Okay, so, the android...android emulator
...any of you guys who have built a mobile application across ios android or windows
...especially those of you who have done android development are probably familiar with
the android simulators that are out there for the ones that are available in free
...pretty slow and for the ones that are
good they're actually quite expensive so one of the things that we heard from a lot of android developers
was that we should introduce an android developer and that's actually included as part of visual studio
twenty fifteen so you can go ahead and just get this now you could do all
kinds of configurations you can get whatever is the latest api and this runs on
hyper v so it actually is complimentary to the windows phone emulator used to be that
you had to do a complete rebootwith your...set reset your biased so that you hat
...using the other virtualization technologies now this works kind-of
directlyin your app so what I'm going to do now is I'm just going to
take as sample and in this case I'm going to take a.
Cplus-plus component.
The...eighty-six version of it and I'm just going to
drag-and-drop and educate directly onto the android
emulator up I did this before I need to attach the.
...attached the device I can't have two instances of ab running at the same time.
Ok, let's restart this.
...will take just a second.
Rh once this loads I can actually just go ahead and drag-and-drop the ap
k directly on to the emulator.
...pretty cool demo.
Ok,
so, now using my touch enabled pc I can go ahead and drag-and-drop this
onto the device that's installed properly now I just need to go and launch
it so as you see this is an open gl version of an application
running the common kind of mighty...an example and if
I can rotate it and rotated again I can, you know,
spin that and it's actually pretty responsive so I get a full.
Experience here I can even.
Should be able to this might be a little bit warm but I can even do multi touch,
for example,...zoom in and out?
Zoom in and out to the application so the
android emulator is a full image of android running
on your pc and you can run native applications or.
Or java base applications
or examine based applications or apache cordova applications
...so with that note let's jump to apache
cordova.
Now for this I'm going to jump to this other machine.
This is six I believe.
So, one of the things that.
Sorry just need to pull out this...
...it went to sleep...there we go.
Shuttle at one and just try that.
There we go okay.
One of the things that we're pretty excited about is with the visual
studio the twenty fifteen extension.
We now have templates
for the ironic and...you I have you guys ever heard of
iconic anybody here...new I okay they're pretty good
templates for building hybrid applications so I can build a
...of application using javascript or
...a...or types script how many you guys have heard of types
...before great you should definitely go check out anders
...session tomorrow where he'll be talking about tightrope one-point-five and I don't have the
templates installed on this machine but if I jump back
to this machine real quick I can show you them work...
So, if we go to file.
New project so these are pretty popular ui frameworks
for building web-based applications so as you can see here this is
kind of like a simple to do list style application.
While I'm doing this I might as well just go ahead and launch it we can ignore that.
And, you'll see it...in and in the meantime I'll show you the my shuttle application
as well the driver version of the application and I can
go ahead and launch this in the ripple emulator which is a version of
chrome that is optimized for running hybrid applications and.
The should run in just a second and...we're doing that.
Let's jump back to this application so for the
...application for the cordova app as you can see one of the things that we've
done between the preview that we launched last fall and
therc that were launching today is we've actually made it a file-based
project system so that actually mirrors the cordova
project itself how did you guys have heard of apache cordova before.
Okay, how many of you guys have heard of phone gap before okay
they're actually somewhat one in the same thorough few differences if you're really,
really deeply involved but,
for the most part they're they refer to the same technology and apache cordova
is a project that adobe donated to the apache foundation a couple a
few years ago now and it basically does two things number one
in abstracts away the notion of the
platform specific packaging technology across iowa's android
and windows so that you as a developer don't have to worry about that quite as
much of the other thing that does is it actually makes it very easy for you to access native
device capabilities and then it normalize is those native api is across a
...api front-end so I'll show you guys that just a second but,
what you can see here is that the way that this is defined is very much like any
kind of web application but the client portion of that web application so there's a dubbed uproot
and it I have css I have scripts?
this is where most of my application is defined and I have in
the cs as you can see that I'm using less which is a common css preprocessor and,
if we go to the
scripts and the type things you can actually see that I'm using angular js
...app I'm using j query in this app to the point is for cordova
base applications if you're a web developer this will feel very familiar to you can use the
same comment web-based frameworks that you are using today you can use the
same common web-based and experiences for workflow that
you're using today so that's how we're defining it and the next thing I'll show
you guys is that for apache cordova applications we have a conflict
file now this is where you define the application-specific information
for your app as you can see here there is common information per app but if we go
into the windows are android or ios there is
some specific information that you need to specify here but,
the most important thing is the capability of accessing
plugins now the plugins are the way that you can access
native device capabilities per device and then they get normalized so someone
create the plug-in for ios android and windows
and then they expose it to this common plug-in repository with a comment
javascript api surface area now you can get these from
the common repository in this case a lot are coming from the apache cordova
plugins but, you can also get some that are define, you know,
microsoft has contributed some adobe has some to lehrer has some there is
a wide variety of community contributors that are defining these
plugins and in addition to the plugins that are available
to the public I can also define my own plugins so let's say I had my
...sensor that I wanted to use for my application for my mobile apps
I could actually define that censor using native code and then be able to access it from
a...apache cordova application and I can do
that with the custom I can actually go ahead and get something directly off of get.
So, next thing I'm going to do is just launch this to the android emulator.
Which we already have running?
So, across all of these experiences cplus-plus csharp html
javascript what we've tried to do is to make sure that there are comments set of
a characteristics that you guys have come to expect from visual studio that
are uniform across all of the different technologies depending on which technology
use so that you don't have to worry about that number one is the acquisition experience the
...experience is really,
really simple for your depth box number two the debugging and editing
experience that you guys are used to having in visual studio for your code or
against windows applications actually also works against I
was an android doesn't matter which a.
Platform your using.
Now...to do is go to the debug window let's just make it so...you can see these
two side-by-side.
And, I'm going to go to the donned explore and look at the index...html.
And, now I can use this select elements to just
...element on the screen that has actually updated the dom explore
lives so I'm attached in this debug mode I can go ahead just that you guys can see it and make
this a little more obvious and you can see that we have
updated the application live in the emulator now I can go ahead and just
edit this html directly and I can just-say-no rides and
cursor often you actually see that I get that directly updated so this makes that the
workflow for developing application extremely rapid and iterative
as you develop your app I can go ahead and start the service.
I think I forgot to
celebrate point on this machine but if we go ahead and.
The solution explore.
If I go into the.
Scripts.
Let's see.
Well, let's skip...break point for now but,
anyways the point is that you can actually stop in the debug
mode and be able to see your break points and
have the rapid debug experience for that as well?
Now the other thing that we've done in one of the benefits as you can see were hitting the break...now one
of the benefits of having a file-based workflow are project system
for apache cordova projects is that you can use all kinds of,
you know, and, pm or file-based tools against your patchy
...project so if you use gulp or
grunts you can use that in this application and in fact we have a
...json editor here second bring up the
json and I can you can actually see here that I
...you know, the this is using the type script
alpha but I get statement completion I should get statement
completion for angular it looks like that is not coming up right now.
Okay.
The point is that you
actually get integration with all of these all of these.
And,...and file system based experiences if we go to the goal
file you can see that how many...you guys have ever heard of goal.
Of those web developer...I can actually use a gulp file to
...to get the latest packages that
I have a dependency on in my quart of application.
And, in fact I can even go to a task runner so if I go to.
Tools let's see...
go to other windows I can actually see the task runner explore.
And, you can see that this is bound to this is a way that I can visualize the task
runners that are attached to be a my
...file in visual studio so if I if I build this.
You can see that it actually runs the before build process so I actually have
the same workflow across with the frameworks and with the goal
file or bauer or whatever actually running in the context of visual studious this
is a very kind of productive environment now the next thing I'm going to do is to show you
guys the application insights integration and.
So, if we go back to the can think file here let's just close this
at one of the things I can do we have been working on a.
...plug-in for apache
cordova applications and we have that available as a get on the get repository
here one of the things I can do is just take this address right here and copy
it and pasted directly into my visual studio solutions I can go to custom
go to get and I can go ahead and paste that and hit, you know.
This is okay I don't need to run the application anymore.
Let's close thisdoesn't look like the download is working but basically that is
how I would be able to attached to the get repository to get this app
insights app now what I'm going to do is show you what that does there's a
little bit of code that I have to do to create the custom events but,
everything else that you're going to see here comes automatically so if I go to https?
The portal.
That asher.
Dot com I am not connected to network that's great that would explain a
Ok.
Let's try this again.
I'm just going to continue their.
The same password.
So, now we can see the app
...which we just announced today is available for public beta
and...appears if you have any questions you-can come up and ask her
about that and what I'm going to do is go into my asher account and see
what...data and getting back for this application that's deployed into the wild
it does not look to be here so I'm going to switch to this machine again?
Note was working on this machines so we'll bring it up here.
Okay, you can see that I'm logged in here and we see that the
...dot cordova application is there now there's a number of things
that come automatically for mobile applications if you use app insights or application
insights and first of all sessions page views.
What we've done some work to integrate crashes here and this is from
the hockey app acquisition that we did earlier you can also see that I can see the
top devices so if I go into top devices you can actually see
that I can see all of the different device models that are using my applications so this is...you know,
iphone six surface pro
...the different operating systems that are running my app?
And, then the other thing I can do is look at custom events so as I mentioned earlier and there will be some deep
dives on this I can actually create my own custom code to.
Complete a journey, for example, an
and track that task and see what happens with that task so,
in this case you can see that I have
...hundred and twelve people have completed the journey I actually know at how many
of them are on which version of the applications one of the things that I heard from a customer just
the other day was that they just don't have any idea which version of
the application most of their users are actually running the other thing I can do is actually
atta chart here so I can come into?
App insights add a charge.
And, go down here and just click on the tripped cost.
And, you can see that in just a second it will
...to show me what the average trip cost
was across all of the different users of this application so that's a pretty cool
feature gives you insight into both the usage what mobile apps
...mobile devices...running on as well as custom
insight into the different workflows that they went through in the application
...right I think that is the end of my demos so I'm going to kind of
jump back to the slides real quick the powerpoint ok so
...you can basically build rich native applications across multiple,
multiple platforms windows ios...android and you can reuse the code across all
of those different solutions and you share the app logic across
the different platforms and using a dot net portable classed libraries you can actually
share the exact same binary as you can do share the unit testing and things like that and,
one hundred-percent of the api zer...so our good friends ameri
and are very good about releasing updates to the sdk...soon as the
...of the operating systems releases updates to their api...
In terms of you I design as I showed you guys we have
...way designers directly in visual studio so
that you can do drag-and-drop kinds of app construction for your app and the way that
this...apps are produced is that the actually end up
with new essentially native compact natively compiled applications running ios
...android so for ios it does ahead of time compilation to produce the
armed binary which is basically what the ios apps
do and for android it uses the just-in-time compilation
...the entry device across the windows universal apps you can share
...animal across all of the different devices and then
you can tailor the experience for each of the devices.
And, for the cross platform cplus-plus components you can actually build
a shared component or as...will show you later
today I believe he will show you that you can actually build entirely native activities
in cplus-plus using visual studio and then you can take
...share components and build the presentation...in salmon or cordova.
The visual studio emulator for android is a fast x eighty-six image
and it runs on hyper v so you don't need to reboot tobias to get this
to work and it comes with visual studio as you guys know we
have the visual studio community the version so you can actually get
that for free and the visual studio emulator is included as part of that it speaks
...debugging so I don't need to do any kind of custom thing or
get another tool to be able to attaching the debug are for that and I get all of
the native device capabilities and sensors in that emulator.
The patchy cordova tools make it easy to build hybrid html
base applications so basically this is a javascript html.
Or...script or...application that you end up building and
then it gets packaged as a native apps for each one of the different platforms so you can
send push notifications and you can get all kinds of real-time information from the
sensors on the device and then with types script which if you haven't if
you're javascript developer today and you have not heard or tried of type tried
type script...highly encourage you to go to anders session tomorrowwe introduce
types script because as we heard from a lot of customers who
are starting to build very large web applications with
hundreds of thousands of lines of code was it was hard to manage javascript
applications that are of that size so, types script ads strong,
strong typing to javascript so you can get the code productivity
that you get...csharp but for javascript based applications so that's what type script is
and the type script experience is throughout
our cordova tooling so you get gratin tele sense for all of the plug-in
completion or for any of the native device capabilities with the cordova
applications and the tooling in visual studio you can get you can use
any javascript framework that you use in your web development today or
...common command line tools like and pm grunt gulp, you know,
bauer all of those kinds of task winner kinds of tools.
And, you end up building a single hybrid application across ios android and windows.
Now this was intended to be an overview sessions so that you guys
could see everything that we had to offer in terms of a
across platform mobile development.
What I've done here is I've highlighted a couple of sessions that will go deeper on each
one of these topics if you...hear more about the app service...a bunch of sessions on that if you want
to hear more about across platforms cplus-plus more sessions on that cordova more sessions
...more sessions so this is the overview session if you want
to go deep on any of these topics I highly encourage you to check that out and, in terms of
...resources you guys can go get these bits today go try it now so,
get visual studio twenty fifteen
rc go try the app service on the website that I showed you guys and,
definitely try the application insights
data that wasn't quite public yet so there is no link to send them too but?
Definitely go check that out as well and again please
...fill out an email so thank you very much.